Finding Aid for William S. Benninghoff papers, 1943-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William S. Benninghoff papers 1943-2000, 1968-1986
Benninghoff, W. S.
3.5 linear feet
2009172 Aa 2
Botany professor and Director of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens at the University of Michigan; records include administrative and research files related to his positions with the university.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Anne S. Benninghoff (donor no. 6362 ) in 2006.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Williams S. Benninghoff, born in Fort Wayne, Indiana on March 23, 1918, was a professor of Botany at the University of Michigan from 1957 to 1988, and served as Director of the Matthaei Botanical Gardens from 1977 to 1986. He studied for his S.B. (1940), M.A. (1942), and Ph.D. (1948) degrees at Harvard University. From 1943 to 1946 he served as a deck officer in the United States Navy before returning to Harvard to complete his studies. After finishing his Ph.D. work in botany in 1948, he worked as a botanist for the U.S. Geological Survey and was head of the Alaska Terrain and Permafrost Section. He came to the University of Michigan in 1957 as an Associate Professor of Botany, and was appointed to full professor in 1960.
Benninghoff's early research activities included phytosociological studies, glacial geological field work, and the terrain and ecology of Antarctica. His later work focused on applying his palynological skills to the analysis of Quaternary vegetation and the dissemination of pollen and spores in the atmosphere. He published numerous articles in his field and has been widely cited.
Benninghoff's service to the University of Michigan's Matthaei Botanical Gardens spanned two decades. He served as Curator of Ecological Collections (1966-1986), Assistant Director (1965-1966), Acting Director (1975) and Director (1977-1986). During this time he oversaw the gardens' 75th Anniversary Celebration in 1982, the day-to-day administrative functions of the gardens, and supervised ongoing ecological research projects based on the gardens' lands and plant collections.
He was also an active member of the teaching faculty, supervising the work of many doctoral students and teaching in the areas of general ecology, plant ecology, physiology, geography, limnology, oceanography, and biotics. He also served on several university committees during his tenure on the faculty, and received numerous awards for his accomplishments, including the Department of Interior Meritorious Service Award, 1954; the Antarctic Service Medal of the United States, 1973; and the Hiroshima (Japan) University Commemorative Medal, 1974. Upon his retirement in 1988, he was named Professor Emeritus of Botany
Benninghoff passed away on January 25, 1993 at the age of 74, and is interred at Arlington National Cemetery.
The W. S. Benninghoff collection consists of three series: Botany Department, Matthaei Botanical Gardens, and University of Michigan Biological Station. The strength of the collection is its documentation of the administrative aspects of the Botany Department and Matthaei Botanical Gardens in the 1970s and 1980s.
Subjects:
Benninghoff, W. S.; Botany.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.
- Botany Department 1957-1990
  The first series, Botany Department (1.5 linear feet, 1957-1990), documents Benninghoff's research, teaching, and administrative activities as a member of the Botany Department and Division of Biological Sciences from 1957 to 1983. Materials include chronological files, administrative files, and documents related to Benninghoff's committee work and teaching responsibilities. The administrative files' strength lies in their documentation of Benninghoff's role in shaping departmental policies and programs. The committee files are strong in their documentation of Benninghoff's role in the shaping and ultimate discontinuance of the Interdepartmental Program in Ecology, the Botany Department's graduate program, and the reorganization of the Biology Department in the early 1970s. The teaching materials are mostly syllabi and reading lists for courses that Benninghoff taught.
  - Chronological Files 1960-1988, 16 folders (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    - Administrative
      - Botany Concentration Program 1960-1961 (Box 1)
      - Botany Faculty, Biographical Information 1977-1983 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1970-1990 (Box 1)
      - Department Evaluation 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      - Department Policies 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      - Department Review 1962-1963 (Box 1)
      - Department Seminars 1973-1975 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Business 1957-1960 (Box 1)
      - Herbarium 1972-1977 (Box 1)
      - Systematic and Evolutionary Biology Program 1964 (Box 1)
    - Committees
      - Awards Committee 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - Consensus Committee 1968 (Box 1)
      - Graduate Affairs Committee 1972-1975, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Interdepartmental Ecology Program 1958-1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Remote Sensing Program Committee 1977-1979 (Box 2)
      - Reorganization of Biology Department Committee 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - School of Public Health, Environmental and Industrial Health (Box 2)
      - Department Review Committee 1976-1982 (Box 2)
      - University Lands Committee 1965-1983, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Teaching
      - Biology 112 1986 (Box 2)
      - Botany 125/160, Plant Geography 1957, undated (Box 2)
      - Botany 190, Plants, Man, and Environment 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - Botany 202, Practical Botany undated (Box 2)
      - Botany/Zoology 351, General Ecology 1973 (Box 2)
      - Botany 428, Caribbean Marine Environments 1975 (Box 2)
      - Botany 808, Plant Physiology Seminar 1970 (Box 2)
      - Course Evaluation Forms 1977 (Box 2)
      - Course Re-numbering 1986 (Box 2)
      - Course Schedules undated, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
      - Proposed Courses 1975, 1987 (Box 2)
      - Zoology 62, General Ecology 1957 (Box 2)
      - Zoology 242, Biotic Communities undated (Box 2)
      - Zoology 802, Limnology and Oceanography Seminar 1961-1962 (Box 2)
- Matthaei Botanical Gardens 1943-2000
  The Matthaei Botanical Gardens (1.5 linear feet, 1943-2000) series contains materials related to Benninghoff's tenure as Assistant Director, Acting Director, and Director. The series documents his role in the administrative functioning of the gardens, as well as research studies undertaken at the gardens while he was Director. The series is especially strong in documenting Benninghoff's various administrative functions including fundraising, long-term planning, staff and executive committee meetings, and visitor guides. The Research Activities files contain research proposals, general research reports, and results of specific research studies undertaken at the gardens.
  - Administrative
    - 75th Anniversary 1982 (Box 2)
    - American Association of Botanical Gardens Workshop 1978 (Box 2)
    - Annual Report Preparation Contributions, Notes, and Memorandums 1975-1978 (Box 2)
    - Botanical Gardens Guide 1962-1975 (Box 2)
    - Botany 303, Selected Plants in the Botanical Gardens undated (Box 2)
    - Botany 351 Conservatory Demonstrations 1975 (Box 2)
    - Budget 1981-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1977-1987 (Box 2)
    - Current Business 1982 (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Friends and Members 1985-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Fundraising 1981-1985, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - General Information 1976-1983 (Box 3)
    - Guide to Future Development, Draft 1982 (Box 3)
    - Guide to Future Development 1983 (Box 3)
    - Helen V. Smith Garden Dedication, Notes 1991 (Box 3)
    - Historical Information 1943-1998 (Box 3)
      (includes earlier photocopied material)
    - Long Range Planning 1985 (Box 3)
    - Maps 1982 (Box 3)
    - Master Planning 1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets 1983-2000 (Box 3)
    - Plantings 1967-1986, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Remarks to Staff 1977 (Box 3)
    - Safety Shoes 1979 (Box 3)
    - Seed Catalogs 1965 (Box 3)
    - Staff Meetings 1977-1985, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Superintendent of Buildings and Grounds Position 1978 (Box 3)
    - Tour Guide Manual 1979 (Box 3)
    - Trail Guide 1980 (Box 3)
  - Research Activities
    - Alternatives to Petroleum-Based Agriculture 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1978-1984 (Box 3)
    - Ford Foundation Research Proposal 1977 (Box 3)
    - Interdisciplinary Research Group 1983 (Box 3)
    - Notes on Research Projects, undated 1978, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Planning for Research 1982 (Box 3)
    - Report to Vice President of Research on Botanical Gardens Research Activities 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Sediment Distribution and Landform Classification of the University of Michigan Botanical Garden undated (Box 3)
    - Sulfur Research 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Surficial Geology and Geomorphology of the Dixboro Botanical Gardens Site undated (Box 4)
    - Tissue Culture Program 1981-1982, 4 folders (Box 4)
- University of Michigan Biological Station 1957-1977
  The final series, University of Michigan Biological Station (0.5 linear feet, 1957-1977) documents Benninghoff's involvement with the station between 1975 and 1977. It includes directories, correspondence, registration information and receipts, documentation of research activities, and vegetation maps.
  - Correspondence 1960-1970 (Box 4)
  - Directories 1957, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Registration Information and Receipts 1961 (Box 4)
  - Research Activities 1961 (Box 4)
  - Summer 1966 (Box 4)
  - Vegetation Maps 1969-1970 (Box 4)